[SPEAKER_00]: Here's some excerpts from Majjhima Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll try and include the PDF file from which I'm reading as well, maybe in a link or so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this first bit is from Majjhima Nikaya 52.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, householder, quite secluded from central pleasures, secluded from unwholesome states, a bhikkhu enters upon and abides in the first jhāna, which is accompanied by applied and sustained thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's a translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: With rapture and pleasure born of seclusion,
[SPEAKER_00]: He considers this and understands it thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first jhāna is conditioned and volitionally produced.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as it says here, he considers this and understands it thus, not before or after his jhāna, but while he dwells in that jhāna with the pleasure born of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this should dispel any notion
[SPEAKER_00]: That some people might have that in jhāna your thinking stops and you're absorbed in some sort of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a clarity of vision, unshakable mindfulness and pleasure born of seclusion from the unwholesome states, a sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the pleasure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a proper thinking in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in proper, it's not rooted in greed, aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not affected by by central domain, by the domain of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once the mind is established like that, he considers and understands it thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first jhāna is conditioned and intentionally, volitionally produced.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whatever is conditioned and intentionally produced is a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's subject to cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he recognizes that even such a lofty state, such as the first jhāna in this case, the state that it's beyond everything unwholesome, that it's utterly wholesome, as there's nothing, nothing, eh... rooted in greed, aversion, delusion in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he recognizes that as pure as this state is, even this state is determined by the intention to develop this state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined by his efforts, it's determined by his understanding, it's determined by the clarity of his mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When those things cease, when his existence ceases in that manner, then this jhāna, as lofty as it is, cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reason why the Buddha emphasizes this very often in various suttas, it's because, eh... obviously, there is no clarity of discernment when one is still rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... when one is rooted in wholesome, such as in the case of first jhāna, if one turns his mind towards the nature of the arisen phenomena at the time, he'll see that it still shares the same nature as other things, even when the mind is not in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things such as cannot be owned, arisen on its own, it's impermanent, oppresses you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the characteristics of the determinations,
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason why it's always... what we say on the basis of wholesome is just in case there are any... any... any tendencies, any other sort of subtler notions, eh... that one might not have considered, they will be considered on the basis of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, eh... it will add like a... it will work like a blanket inside, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one... if one understands that the nature of impermanence, the nature of suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is subjected to its cessation on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one understands that on the basis of first jhāna, means nothing else inferior to that can remain unaffected by that understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... and that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we go further here, it says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: If he steadies his mind in that... in that discernment, in that understanding, not in that mystical experience, but in a clarity of understanding that this is impermanent,
[SPEAKER_00]: He attains the destruction of the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he doesn't attain the destruction of the taints, and still has some desire for the dhamma, the delight in the dhamma, then with the destruction of the five lower fetters, he becomes one due to reappear spontaneously in the pure abode, and there attain finally bhāna without ever returning from that world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he becomes, eh... anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is one thing proclaimed by the Blessed One, who knows and sees accomplished and fully enlightened, wherein, if a bhikkhu abides diligent, ardent and resolute, his unliberated mind comes to be liberated, his undestroyed tends come to be destroyed, and he attains the supreme security from bondage that he had not attained before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the basis of first jhāna to be used for direct insight into the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, further, in the in the same sutta, it says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, what on earth is the path, the way to the abandoning of the five lower fetters?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, with the seclusion from the acquisitions, with the abandoning of the unwholesome states, with the calming of bodily inertia, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, it's included from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: A bhikkhu enters upon and abides in the first jhāna, which is accompanied by thinking and pondering, with rapture and pleasure born of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that monk discerns whatever exists within that experience as a material form, feeling, perception, determinations and consciousness,
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees those states as impermanent, as suffering, as disease, as a tumor, as a barb, as a calamity, as an affliction, as an alien, as disintegrating, as a void, as not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: While he's in that experience, that will turn his mind away from those states.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he directs it towards the deathless element, thus, this is the peaceful, this is the sublime, the stilling of all determinations, the relinquishing of all attachments, the destruction of craving, dispassion, cessation, nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he's steady in that, he attains the destruction of the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it goes on saying the same as for the previous passage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's either discerning the nature of the determination, as in, even the wholesome states, they do result in a sense of safety from... and pleasure and rapture born from that seclusion, from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one discerns the nature of them, the universal nature of the arisen phenomena, one will see that it's still subjected to same things of impermanence and suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of that, anything inferior to it cannot remain unaffected, as we said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second part, the second way, is to to look at the, eh... whatever exists in terms of the material forms of the
[SPEAKER_00]: To look at the things, the phenomena, as in the way of aggregates, whichever... the experience as a whole, in its more general peripheral nature, which is the nature of aggregates, to see it as unwanted, to see it as dangerous, as it says here, as a disease, as a tumor, as a barb, as a calamity, as an affliction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he knows that by seeing it like that, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any inferior desire that he might have towards particular things that are manifested through his senses, cannot remain unaffected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he is experiencing a thorough dispassion towards the nature of the form, the nature of the feeling, the nature of perception, determinations and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just this particular form, or that particular feeling, or this particular perception, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the mind is properly developed in terms of that peripheral awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can apply it onto that level of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the particular absorption with one or the other particular concern, but the fundamental nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: If things are applied there, no particular concern can affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, here's one from Majmuka 5.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, here, friend, this person with a blemish, who does not know as it really is, there is a blemish in me, he would not arouse interest and make effort to dispel that blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he would die with a defiled mind, with greed, hate and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one thing probably can be mentioned here is that it's not any random blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like some so obvious thing that
[SPEAKER_00]: That a person is tolerating, that he knows it's bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it says, he would die with defiled mind, with greed, aversion, greed, hate and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the blemishes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that... that must be a standard and a criteria that should not be compromised.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, even if somebody starts with the... with the practice, eh... they can't say, okay, well, you know, I'm a putujana, so thus, of course, I have greed, aversion, delusion, but I'm still practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying that, eh... removes the responsibility for greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if there is a removal of responsibility for it, there cannot be effort applied for its uprooting.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're delaying it, you're not going to be dealing with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, it's not going to happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nobody says that you should think it will happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that you should then, in the meantime, so to speak, ignore responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it takes you 10 years to develop the right view, well, for 10 years you have to feel the weight of responsibility for greed, aversion, delusion and never turn away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you actually take responsibility for your own greed, aversion, delusion in such manner, it won't take you 10 years to see through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why people don't see through greed, aversion, delusion is because they're delayed, because they don't take responsibility, because, as this sutta says, he does not see there is a blemish in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, what he thinks blemish is,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's usually not... or it's like the obvious blemish, but not the blemish that the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, his criteria of blemish is not sufficiently developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you regard greed, aversion, delusion, doesn't matter what particular exemplification of those underlying tendencies there, all you care is that greed, aversion or delusion is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the... that's the work there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing less than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there is a second type of person, is the person with a blemish, who knows as it really is.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a blemish in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, he can then dispel that blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would die... he would die with a non-defiled mind, without greed, hate and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he recognized that that's the threshold for... of blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he undone it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, suppose a bronze dish were bought from a shop or a smithy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be covered with dust and stains and the owner would use it and have it cleaned and would not put it away in a dusty corner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would the bronze dish then get mortified and stay later on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, too, friend, a person with the blemish, who knows it really, there is a blemish in me, would arouse interest and make the effort to dispel that blemish.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he would die with a non-defiled mind, without greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, now there's again Majjhima Nikāi.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might have read this before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anyway, it's a good passage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cunda, the idea that one...
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the Buddha saying this.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that one who has himself sunk into the mud can pull out another who has sunk into the mud, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that the one who has not sunk into the mud can pull out another who has sunk into the mud, that's possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that the one who himself is untamed, untrained, unextinguished, can tame, train, help extinguish other, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that one who himself is tamed, trained, extinguished, can tame, train, help extinguish another, that is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, let's see this one.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Majjhima 13.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's see what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Friends, the recluse Gautama describes the full understanding of central pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we do so too.
[SPEAKER_00]: The recluse Gautama describes the full understanding of matter, as in rūpa, and we do so too.
[SPEAKER_00]: The recluse Gautama describes the full understanding of feelings, and we do so too.
[SPEAKER_00]: What then is the distinction here, friends?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the variance?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the difference between the recluse Gautama's teaching and our teaching, between his instruction and ours?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha says, because wanderers of other sects who speak thus should be questioned in this manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But friends, what is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the escape in the case of sensual pleasures?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the escape in the case of matter?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the escape in the case of feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being questioned thus, wanderers of other sects will fail to account for the matter, and what is more, they will get into difficulties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's not their province.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I see no one in the world with its god, its Mahārāja, its Brāhmaṇas, in its generation with the Recklessness and Brāhmaṇas, with its princes and its people, who would satisfy the mind with a reply to these questions, except for the Tathāgata or his disciple or the one who has learned it from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people might wonder, so why, why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is, why no other sects can, other teachings can explain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, when the Buddha says, eh... the gratification, the danger and the escape, in case of sensuality, in case of matter, in case of feelings, means full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means full understanding of the duration, of the arisen phenomena, of the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the particular sensuality, a particular sensual desire, but the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, possibilities of sensuality are already with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the domain of matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: What we said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: The general nature of feeling, the general nature of matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the escape?
[SPEAKER_00]: All that...
[SPEAKER_00]: is on the basis of the presently... Let's take feeling, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the escape in case of feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these three aspects are all on the basis of the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not three separate things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just three things to discern within the presently enduring feeling, or the presently enduring matter, or the presently enduring sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the gratification of these things, like the gratification of feelings, it's the... say, let's put it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gratification in the feelings is the possibility and the actuality of the pleasure you can derive from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, when it goes your way, when it obeys you, when it doesn't oppress you, when it offers even more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the genuine gratification in feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a genuine gratification in matter as well, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: When the matter obeys you, when obeys your sense of control, assumed sense of control, when obeys your will, intentionality, when fulfills your projected notions of ideas and desires, there is the gratification in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like an offer, offer of ownership that you get verified to an extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, you feel gratified to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even the offer of ownership is on the basis of that presently enduring thing, which already means it's impermanent, because you are not responsible for its presence, nor for its endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these random feelings that arise,
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, when you think, oh, it's given to me to be perceived, you're perceiving that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That notion is also within the notion of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not that from which the matter has been given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any notion that matter has been given to you is thus a wrong notion, because it requires you to step outside of yourself and to see where the matter comes from to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's inconceivable, because even that thought is within that perception that was given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that matter that was given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you recognize that there is no external that you can think of without misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fully enclosed within the five aggregates as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, experience of external, it's internal, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said, eh... if a monk remembers his previous life, or five previous lives, or five hundred previous lives, all he remembers is the five aggregates or one among them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's... that's experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think outside of it, that's within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not incidental that the ātavāda, the self-view, corresponds to the gratuitous notion of a self-master, controller, independent of your experience as a whole, as in external to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly where it's rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anyway, let's get... the gratification means that the degree that you can exercise your will, your control, your ownership,
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that that... even that degree as a possibility is secondary to that independent arising of that thing, whatever that thing is, be it matter or feeling or sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see it, you take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And taking for granted that kind of relative... offer of relative ownership means absolute ownership for you, because that's all you took, that's all you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the gratification in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people remain bound with their ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because there is a mystical secret hidden behind a veil of illusion or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because of their own very ignorant intentions and acts that they can't say no to, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it says, what is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can you can pause the talk now and think about yourself based on what we said about the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about what is the danger then.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the gratification is the offer of that relative ownership that ends up pretty much intoxicating people, what is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Accept that intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger that's on the same level
[SPEAKER_00]: As that offer prospect of pleasure, of gratification, of control, of mastery, of verification of your own assumed sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger that's simultaneously there as a second aspect?
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is exactly rooted in the same thing where the gratification is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, if you're just looking along the barrel of gratification, all you're gonna see is the prospects of your gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing the nature of the basis upon which that gratification has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing the nature of the feeling, in the case we are discussing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you if you don't take gratification for granted, you just see it as a prospect, as a possibility, but you don't see it as your right, and you're certainly not careless in regard to it, then you see that gratification that has arisen on the on the basis of the presently enduring feeling on its own, that I'm subjected to,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I go with gratification, I cannot remain seeing the present enduring feeling on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I will automatically...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not even a matter of choice, as in, I will have to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You automatically, by following gratification at its face value, you automatically appropriate that which is independent of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which doesn't care about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your feelings don't care about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are invisible to your own feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for them, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: You exist only because you keep assuming your own existence as the master controller of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't follow gratification at its face value, then you don't automatically assume yourself to be the owner of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you don't assume, you recognize how dangerous it is then.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger there.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that there is a feeling, that offer of gratification, offer of confirmation of your ownership, offer of confirmation of your will, intentionality, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the offer is rooted in the presently enduring thing that you have no say in, which means it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will come to cease and you can't even, like, conceive it how that would not be the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking such basis for granted is then dangerous because it's going to affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot remain indifferent if you have taken the gratification of your feeling for granted and then followed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that feeling changes, you will be affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the third aspect is understanding the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the escape in the case of feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is the escape, what we just described.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of gratification and full understanding of the danger means developing the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you
[SPEAKER_00]: Genuinely recognize the danger of taking the arisen feeling as mine, taking it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not entertain that notion of appropriation and gratification for not even for a second longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the most perilous thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus, you escape it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's in Majjhima Nikaya 13, for those who want to read it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, we expanded on it a bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, here's Majjhima 15, that's removing the blemishes, we talked about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, here is an interesting passage, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's Majjhima 17, and it says here, because a bhikkhu abides supported by a person, when abiding, when abiding supported by a person, by a certain person, I suppose, unestablished mindfulness does not get established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unconcentrated mind, uncomposed mind does not get composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That bhikkhu should thus reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: I abide supported by this person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And abiding thus, my unestablished mindfulness does not get established, uncomposed mind does not get composed, undestroyed desire does not get destroyed, unattained noble end of yoke is not attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: As for the four requisites, robes, food dwellings, and medicine, I collect them without difficulty.
[SPEAKER_00]: That bhikkhu should then reflect further.
[SPEAKER_00]: I did not go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a homeless, for the sake of robes, food, dwellings or requisites, when I'm ill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, to me, living supported by this person, not established mindfulness does not get established, not concentrated mind does not concentrate, not destroyed desire does not get destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not attained noble end of yogic is not attained, because that bhikkhu should leave that person without informing them, so that he may not follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: This, eh... this refers to the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think this refers to the teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this refers to a bhikkhu who would live with, under the mentorship, I suppose, of a senior monk, but he's not progressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the monastery might be well supplied by everything that he might need in terms of the requisites, but then he should reflect that that's not why he went forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he should thus leave, not just leave right away, but leave without telling that person so that they can't follow him.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means really prioritizing and reminding yourself why you got into robes in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the life won't last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if a person lives 50 years more, that's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to go very quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without thinking about the end game of, as the Buddha said himself, not attain the noble end,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, one is going to pay the price he probably wasn't ready to bargain for, because the fact that the person was able, first, to come across the Buddha's teaching, secondly, able to leave the household life and actually ordain, that's already quite a fortunate set of circumstances, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, nobody's denying responsibility of people who do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are responsible for their own going forth and everything, so they will take the credit for it, but all of that, in itself, will be a wasted opportunity if a person does not attain the noble end.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they get satisfied with just being a monk or living in a suitable environment, they need to then reflect further and genuinely see whether their mindfulness gets increased, their composure, the right view gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, well, there is no time to waste.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much what this passage is saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's see where this one takes us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Majjhima 11 and says, because there are these two views, the view of being and the view of non-being.
[SPEAKER_00]: The word for being is bhāva, the Pali word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ascetics and brahmins who adhere to the view of being, who are overpowered by the view of being, who hang on to the view of being, they are opposed to the view of non-being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ascetics and brahmins who adhere to the view of non-being, who are overpowered by the view of non-being, who hang on to the view of non-being, they're opposed by the... they're opposed to the view of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ascetic and brahmin who do not understand as they actually are the origin, setting down, the gratification, the danger, and the escape in the case of these two views.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what we talked about just now.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they don't understand those views fully,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ascetic in Brahman who does understand
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's not much to add here, unless...
[SPEAKER_00]: We begin a whole new long discussion about what being is and what non-being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But practically, even passages like this, a person should at least try to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not dismiss, oh, it's just some like generic philosophy or something, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being and non-being, again, in the most fundamental, the most general, peripheral sense,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pretty much either-or.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, it's a... it's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you push things peripherally, you're gonna say they're there or they're not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, the being is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The denying of the being, then you have the non-being.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that non-being, you can designate, you can have a view rooted in it, means even that is a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just the negative denial of the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the Buddha talks like this about the bhava and vibhava, it refers to the absolutely fundamental, most general underlying view of a person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if a person himself pushes and tries to discern his own views as far as he can, he'll see that he's going to be rooted in either fundamentally saying yes to his existence or saying no to his existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: On more particular levels, he might sometimes say yes, sometimes say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, he's going to have a view of yes towards it, or no towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what this means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the annihilationists and internalists, as we will call them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, it wasn't just like...
[SPEAKER_00]: A slur that he developed to dismiss other philosophers of notes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you press those wrong views, they're going to fall into these two categories on the most fundamental, general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ones that say yes, and the ones that say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, for as long as that's the case, then there is lust, anger, delusion, and assumption out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one understands that, that's how one develops the Middle Way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how one is free from lust, anger, delusion and assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Free from ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on a practical basis, a person can reflect, just through asking certain questions to oneself, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing what the notion is... what kind of attitude is present there, for example, eh... when you think about death, the inevitable death, that will have to happen, that nobody wants to think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: To what degree is my sense of self affected?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, most people, if you just pick someone on the street, they say, well, everybody dies, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize they don't really allow
[SPEAKER_00]: the notion of death to affect their sense of self, because it's way too terrifying, which means they fully... they fully kind of encapsulated themselves in a... in a... in a... this protective view of... of my being will be unaffected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, they... on the fundamental level, they refuse to say... they refuse to even allow possibility of no towards their own being.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always a yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even when they face death,
[SPEAKER_00]: Externally witness it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They make sure it doesn't apply to them through their view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their views protect them from having it applied to themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until, of course, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't hide from it forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death will come.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it hasn't been faced while you were alive, then it's too late to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-being would be the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be the denial of the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which again, fundamentally, is a form of being in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's equally binding as a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just through denying it, you assume that what's left after the denial, it's permanent, it's gonna last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you adhere to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, if somebody says, well, see, through denying it, you're still within the nature of being, they will get angry and upset.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would oppose those views.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would oppose the views of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not of a particular being, this and that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fundamental, like, say, like, for example, saying, quite a common view, that we are nothing, but just a bunch of molecules, hormones and organs operating, and just, just basically a physical matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the body breaks apart, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing left.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a form of just denying the validity of the being of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just dismissing it through scientific terms and scientific observations and attributing your own responsibility and properties just to the molecules and hormones and chemicals and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody says, well, see, even that denial that you are engaging in, and then you would be doing so,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through dismissing it, you think you're safe from that which is subjected to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the implication of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, if you were to point out that the notion, eh... in regard to the dismissal of the being, the notion that kind of... it's... it is a background of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that is within the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in order to deny something, that thing needs to be present there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, whether you affirm the being or deny being, that is secondary to the presently arisen bhava.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, whether you affirm the being or deny being, you just end up binding yourself more to the assumption of the validity of that being in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you end up binding yourself even more to that which is subjected to death and destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said when people don't know the escape from being, they end up revolving around the being, through affirming, denying, affirming and denying, neither affirming nor denying, they end up being bound with the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said it's like a dog chained to a post.
[SPEAKER_00]: It tries to escape the post, ends up just running around the post and tying himself tighter and tighter and tighter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's that.